<tool id="anno2gff" name="Anno2GFF">
  <description>Generates a GFF3 file from an annotation gene structure object (AGS)</description>
  <command>~/bin/octave_start_script.sh
    "setup_mgene; galaxy_anno2gff('$Annotation.extra_files_path', '$gff_output');"
    >> $Log_File; ~/bin/cleanup_output.sh $Log_File</command>
  <inputs>
    
    <param format="gann" name="Annotation" type="data" label="Genome Annotation in AGS format" help="Genome annotation file in AGS format."/>
  </inputs>
  <outputs>
     <data format="gff3" name="gff_output" label="Genome annotation in GFF3 format"/>
    <data format="txt" name="Log_File" label="Log File"/>
  </outputs>

  <help>

.. class:: infomark


**What it does**

This tool writes the annotation gene structure (AGS) to a GFF3 file.


.. class:: infomark

**About formats**

**AGS format** Annotation Gene Structure Object is an internal
structure that efficiently stores the information about transcriptionally
active regions or genes.


**GFF format** General Feature Format is a format for describing genes
and other features associated with DNA, RNA and Protein sequences. GFF
lines have nine tab-separated fields::

    1. seqname - Must be a chromosome or scaffold.
    2. source - The program that generated this feature.
    3. feature - The name of this type of feature. Some examples of standard feature types are "CDS", "start_codon", "stop_codon", and "exon".
    4. start - The starting position of the feature in the sequence. The first base is numbered 1.
    5. end - The ending position of the feature (inclusive).
    6. score - A score between 0 and 1000. If there is no score value, enter ".".
    7. strand - Valid entries include '+', '-', or '.' (for don't know/care).
    8. frame - If the feature is a coding exon, frame should be a number between 0-2 that represents the reading frame of the first base. If the feature is not a coding exon, the value should be '.'.
    9. group - All lines with the same group are linked together into a single item.


</help>
</tool>
