<tool id="contenteval_0.3" name="ContentEval" version="0.3">
  <description>Computes performance measures based on content (segment) labels and predictions</description>
  <command>~/bin/octave_start_script.sh "rmpath('/home/galaxy/mgene_galaxy'); addpath('/home/galaxy/svn/projects/mGene_core/'); paths; content_eval('$label', '$label.extra_files_path', '$predictions', '$predictions.extra_files_path', '$performance');"> $Log_File ; ~/bin/cleanup_output.sh $Log_File</command>
  <inputs>
    <param format="cpf" name="label" type="data" label="Content Label file in CPF format" help="The label file contains information about the genomic locations at which a given content type occurs. It can be created with 'Anno2ContentLabel'."/>
    <param format="spf" name="predictions" type="data" label="Content Predictions in SPF format" help="The prediction file, in signal prediction format (SPF), contains a content prediction score for each location. It can be generated with 'ContentPredict'."/>
  </inputs>
  <outputs>
    <data format="txt" name="performance" label="Content prediction performance"/>
    <data format="txt" name="Log_File" label="Log File"/>
  </outputs>
  <help>

**What it does**

This tool takes a label file and a prediction file as input and
computes several measures of accuracy of the predictions.  In
particular, the areas under the Receiver-Operator-Curve (ROC) and the
Precision-Recall-Curve (PRC) are assessed.  Both measures are close to
1.0 for nearly perfect classification; for random guessing they are
close to 0.5 (ROC) and 0.0 (PRC), respectively.

<!--
!!! Typical values for the area under the ROC curve are between 0.XX and
0.YY for some type of content. !!!
-->

------

**Output**

This tool generates a brief accuracy report, stored as a text file for
human inspection.

--------

**Example**

The evaluation of acceptor splice site predictions may look like this::

  Evaluation for "acc" predictions on 981051 positions
   * Area under ROC curve: 0.986
   * Area under PRC curve: 0.854

------

.. class:: infomark

**About formats**

**CPF format** Content Prediction format is similar to the SPF format,
except that it requires exactly an additional field, as it contains
information on segments not on individual positions::

    1. chrom - The name of the chromosome (e.g. chr1, chrY_random).
    2. contentName - possible choices include tss, tis, acc, don, cdsStop, cleave.
    3. scoreName - possible choices include label, output, Conf, Conf_Cum
    4. chromPos1 - The start position of a segment.
    5. chromPos2 - The end position of a segment.
    6. strand - Defines the strand - either '+' or '-'.
    7. score - The score between -infinity and infinity. If scoreName is 'label', then the score should be either -1 or 1.

**SPF format** Content Prediction format was designed for providing information such as labels or predictions for specific genomic locations (with strand information). It has exacty six required fields::

    1. chrom - The name of the chromosome (e.g. chr1, chrY_random).
    2. signalName - possible choices include tss, tis, acc, don, cdsStop, cleave.
    3. scoreName - possible choices include label, output, Conf, Conf_Cum
    4. chromPos - The position in the chromosome. (The first base in a chromosome is numbered 1.)
    5. strand - Defines the strand - either '+' or '-'.
    6. score - The score between -infinity and infinity. If scoreName is 'label', then the score should be either -1 or 1.

</help>
</tool>

